<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Japan Trip 2018</title><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://quarl.es/japan-trip/</id><updated>2018-01-07T22:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Assorted Etiquette Notes</title><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/assorted-etiquette-notes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-07T22:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T22:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>JQ</name></author><id>tag:quarl.es,2018-01-07:/japan-trip/assorted-etiquette-notes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you forget or get something wrong, you'll be fine. This list tops out at &lt;em&gt;faux pas&lt;/em&gt;. Most aren't at that level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shoes off, slippers on&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Won't happen much when out shopping, but when entering a home or anywhere you see one of these raised areas (&lt;em&gt;genkan&lt;/em&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Genkan" src="images/genkan.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take your shoes …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you forget or get something wrong, you'll be fine. This list tops out at &lt;em&gt;faux pas&lt;/em&gt;. Most aren't at that level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shoes off, slippers on&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Won't happen much when out shopping, but when entering a home or anywhere you see one of these raised areas (&lt;em&gt;genkan&lt;/em&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Genkan" src="images/genkan.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take your shoes off. There might be lockers for your shoes if you're entering a restaurant, or if it's a home, there might be a rack, or you might just turn your shoes around and rest them under the ledge. 
And I dunno where the slippers will be, but wear them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General rule: wherever there is one of these divides, shoes stay below. Wear slippers above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes there will be &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; slippers in the bathroom; change your slippers when entering/leaving the bathroom if so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In general, don't eat outside&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not a big deal to most people, but you probably won't see too much of this going on outside of festivals, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think beverages are fine, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put money in the tray when checking out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Put Money Here" src="images/kaikei.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People don't generally pass money directly from hand to hand when checking out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put your money in the tray if there is one (there usually is), and await your change &amp;amp; receipt in that same tray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no tray is present, place your cash on the counter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wait for passengers to exit train before entering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A Train" src="images/train.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably common sense if you've lived in an area with mass transit before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it's busy enough for people to be queued while waiting for the train, just queue with them, or if you're on your own, wait by the side of the door for everyone to come out prior to entering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stand to one side of the escalator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always heard that the specific side to stand to is different in Tokyo vs. Osaka, but never bothered to confirm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any event, if you want to stand still, keep to one side such that you aren't blocking walkers on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't put soy sauce on white rice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's considered weird (hey, I don't write the rules).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there's something else on top of the rice (donburi or something), though, it's fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Separate your trash&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Trash" src="images/trash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In public places this will probably be pretty easy since the bins will be labeled (note, though, that there are &lt;em&gt;barely any trashcans anywhere&lt;/em&gt; in public, compared to the US).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we stay in an air b&amp;amp;b we'll need to figure out &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to sort the trash (it varies by location) and then do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally it'll be some variation of cans, pet (plastic) bottles, non-burnable &amp;amp; burnable garbage being grouped together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't be noisy on the train&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's generally pretty quiet in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you feel awkward checking out in silence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say "onegaishimasu" (oh-neh-guy-shee-mass) or just say "hello" if you want, I dunno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don't have to respond to "irasshaimase"&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clerks will say this (sometimes quite exuberantly) to welcome you into their shop. You don't have to respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Phone Service</title><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/phone-service.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-07T17:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T17:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>JQ</name></author><id>tag:quarl.es,2018-01-07:/japan-trip/phone-service.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You're probably going to want to be able to use your smartphone while we're in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In considering your options, an important first step is to figure out is whether or not your current carrier provides free international roaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, for example, that the plan I use (T-mobile …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You're probably going to want to be able to use your smartphone while we're in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In considering your options, an important first step is to figure out is whether or not your current carrier provides free international roaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, for example, that the plan I use (T-mobile Simple Choice North America) allows for free data roaming (but not calls) in Japan. I had no idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Covered in Japan" src="images/tmobile-roaming.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;However&lt;/em&gt;, that data comes &lt;em&gt;at 2G speeds&lt;/em&gt;, and I'm going to be using my phone to get train directions, etc. So 2G isn't going to cut it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I went ahead and arranged to rent some things.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pocket Wifi&lt;/strong&gt; (LTE speed, unlimited data, up to 10 connected devices, 7 days, will pick up in airport upon arrival). &lt;img alt="Pocket Wifi" src="images/mifi.png"&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://japan-wireless.com/products.html"&gt;Check product details here&lt;/a&gt; (it's the "Premium Wi-Fi" device.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figure that this will at least be a good backup plan for everyone, or perhaps your main source of connectivity depending on how you want to handle things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It came to $60 for the week. Since we'll be sharing it,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;💸 Everyone please give JQ $12. 💸&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the pocket wifi, I arranged (also through &lt;a href="http://japan-wireless.com"&gt;japan-wireless.com&lt;/a&gt;) to rent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;prepaid SIM card&lt;/strong&gt; (Docomo network**, 500mb/day at LTE speed, unlimited slowness thereafter, 7 days). &lt;img alt="sim card" src="images/simcard.png"&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figure that it'll be more convenient than using the pocket wifi while out &amp;amp; about, and it isn't particularly expensive ($30).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in renting one yourself, 🔓&lt;em&gt;you'll need to figure out if your phone is unlocked&lt;/em&gt;🔓.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to do this is to call your carrier and ask them-- be sure to have your IMEI number ready to tell them. You can find the IMEI from &lt;code&gt;Settings&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;General&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;About&lt;/code&gt; on iOS. I'm not sure about Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your phone is not yet fully paid off and/or you're still under contract with your carrier, conventional wisdom seems to hold that it's probably locked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you do want to rent a SIM card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, please talk to JQ so that we can rent it through the same company and have it delivered in the same shipment to the airport. Or feel free to make your own arrangements if desired; just figure that this will be a good way to simplify some of the logistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If your phone is locked but you won't be satisfied with the pocket wifi&lt;/em&gt;, you can rent a phone. I haven't researched this option yet, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Docomo is one of the three major carriers in Japan. They are: Docomo, AU &amp;amp; Softbank.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>