<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Japan Trip 2018 - Logistics</title><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/feeds/logistics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://quarl.es/japan-trip/</id><updated>2018-01-08T22:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Money</title><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/money.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-08T22:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-08T22:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>JQ</name></author><id>tag:quarl.es,2018-01-08:/japan-trip/money.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Let's Get You Some Yen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may be aware, Japan is a primarily cash-based society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this may seem like a step backwards to people used to using credit/debit cards with chips, Apple Pay, etc., I actually quite like it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japanese bills start at the equivalent of a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Let's Get You Some Yen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may be aware, Japan is a primarily cash-based society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this may seem like a step backwards to people used to using credit/debit cards with chips, Apple Pay, etc., I actually quite like it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japanese bills start at the equivalent of a $10 bill, not $1 or $5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those denominations are coins, &lt;em&gt;as they should be&lt;/em&gt; in this day and age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Japanese Coins" src="images/coins.jpg" title="bottom-middle is a 5"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cash is more manageable since you won't have a wallet stuffed full of ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just be sure to manage your coinage. To prevent 1/5/10-coins from accumulating, use them whenever you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you don't have exact change, say, when making a 1,202 yen purchase, go ahead and pay 2,002 yen if you have two one-yen coins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe just buy lots of stuff from vending machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vending Machine" src="images/vending.jpg" title="this one is weird cheap"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side note:&lt;/em&gt; sales tax used to be included in all the prices that you'd see while out &amp;amp; about, but in 2014 the rate was raised to 8% and it ceased to be included. Now it's like what you're used to here. Phooey!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another side note&lt;/em&gt;: you don't &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to use cash all the time in Japan-- &lt;a href="http://youinjapan.net/moving/suica_pasmo_icoca.php"&gt;prepaid IC cards&lt;/a&gt; double as train passes and most people in metropolitan areas have them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;I digress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action plan for money:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call your bank!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days prior to departure (it's too early now), call &amp;amp; let them know that you'll be in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't want to get flagged for fraud just when you need that withdrawal most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Withdraw money from ATMs in Japan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what I've always done, and consensus seems to hold that this is how you get the best exchange rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven Bank ATMs (found in every 7-11) and Post Office Bank ATMs (found in every... post office) can withdraw from foreign accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I'd always used CitiBank ATMs personally, but &lt;a href="http://www.findmyciti.com/jp/"&gt;they are no more&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;I think&lt;/em&gt; I've used a Seven Bank ATM for this purpose before, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sevenbank.co.jp/intlcard/card2.html"&gt;Seven Bank International ATM Service Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Seven Bank ATM" src="images/7bank-atm.jpg" title="I have never used the phone"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.jp-bank.japanpost.jp/en/ias/en_ias_index.html"&gt;Post Office International ATM Service Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Post Office Bank ATM" src="images/yucho-atm.jpg" title="co-op atm where your most valuable resource is teamwork"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll be arriving to Narita terminal 2. &lt;a href="https://www.narita-airport.jp/en/service/svc_12"&gt;Both banks have ATMs there&lt;/a&gt;, so you'll be able to immediately make withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes on ATM usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use them (Seven Bank and Post Office Bank ATMs, at least) in English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was apparently an international ATM scam making the rounds in late 2016, which has resulted in a 50,000-yen daily withdrawal limit (~$500). I figure that ~$1,000/day between the two banks will be plenty. If any of you are bigger ballers than I realize, I dunno, maybe bring your black card or just have your financial advisor look into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japanese ATMs have &lt;em&gt;hours&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes they simply cannot be used, other times they have increased fees (weekends, late-ish night). It isn't really worth worrying about, but is notable in being somewhat &lt;em&gt;bizarre&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I won't be exchanging any money prior to arriving to Narita.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exchanging within the US is apparently pretty ugly, rate-wise (I've never even done it), and there's no particular reason to use a currency exchange service in Chicago (or Narita) since you'll have access to these ATMs in Narita anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If worst comes to worst and you can't use either ATM for some reason (which I don't anticipate), you could visit a currency exchange in Narita.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Currency Exchange" src="images/exchange.png" title="if you must"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So maybe bring some backup dollars for that contingency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.japan-guide.com/e/e2208.html"&gt;Additional reading on the subject of ATMs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Phone Service</title><link href="http://quarl.es/japan-trip/phone-service.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-07T17:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T17:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>JQ</name></author><id>tag:quarl.es,2018-01-07:/japan-trip/phone-service.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You're probably going to want to be able to use your smartphone while we're in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In considering your options, an important first step is to figure out is whether or not your current carrier provides free international roaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, for example, that the plan I use (T-mobile …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You're probably going to want to be able to use your smartphone while we're in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In considering your options, an important first step is to figure out is whether or not your current carrier provides free international roaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, for example, that the plan I use (T-mobile Simple Choice North America) allows for free data roaming (but not calls) in Japan. I had no idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Covered in Japan" src="images/tmobile-roaming.png" title="simple choice north america: use it in japan"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;However&lt;/em&gt;, that data comes &lt;em&gt;at 2G speeds&lt;/em&gt;, and I'm going to be using my phone to get train directions, etc. So 2G isn't going to cut it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I went ahead and arranged to rent some things.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pocket Wifi&lt;/strong&gt; (LTE speed, unlimited data, up to 10 connected devices, 7 days, will pick up in airport upon arrival). &lt;img alt="Pocket Wifi" src="images/mifi.png" title="you can watch tv on it??"&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://japan-wireless.com/products.html"&gt;Check product details here&lt;/a&gt; (it's the "Premium Wi-Fi" device.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figure that this will at least be a good backup plan for everyone, or perhaps your main source of connectivity depending on how you want to handle things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It came to $60 for the week. Since we'll be sharing it,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;💸 Everyone please give JQ $12. 💸&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the pocket wifi, I arranged (also through &lt;a href="http://japan-wireless.com"&gt;japan-wireless.com&lt;/a&gt;) to rent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;prepaid SIM card&lt;/strong&gt; (Docomo network**, 500mb/day at LTE speed, unlimited slowness thereafter, 7 days). &lt;img alt="sim card" src="images/simcard.png" title="i wonder if you'd ever use this without removing the sim card? that bottom left triangle makes u think"&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figure that it'll be more convenient than using the pocket wifi while out &amp;amp; about, and it isn't particularly expensive ($30).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in renting one yourself, 🔓&lt;em&gt;you'll need to figure out if your phone is unlocked&lt;/em&gt;🔓.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to do this is to call your carrier and ask them-- be sure to have your IMEI number ready to tell them. You can find the IMEI from &lt;code&gt;Settings&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;General&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;About&lt;/code&gt; on iOS. I'm not sure about Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your phone is not yet fully paid off and/or you're still under contract with your carrier, conventional wisdom seems to hold that it's probably locked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you do want to rent a SIM card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, please talk to JQ so that we can rent it through the same company and have it delivered in the same shipment to the airport. Or feel free to make your own arrangements if desired; just figure that this will be a good way to simplify some of the logistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If your phone is locked but you won't be satisfied with the pocket wifi&lt;/em&gt;, you can rent a phone. I haven't researched this option yet, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Docomo is one of the three major carriers in Japan. They are: Docomo, AU &amp;amp; Softbank.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>